<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Science | SciRuby]]></title>
  <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/categories/science/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sciruby.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-10-23T20:55:53+09:00</updated>
  <id>http://sciruby.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[SciRuby]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Call for funding: more women needed in open source science software]]></title>
    <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/2013/11/01/call-for-funding-more-women-needed-in-open-source-science-software/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-01T16:24:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://sciruby.com/blog/2013/11/01/call-for-funding-more-women-needed-in-open-source-science-software</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.ncwit.org/blog/did-you-know-demographics-technical-women">Women make up 51% of the American workforce, and yet only 20% of software engineers are female.</a> Worldwide,
the situation is similar. <a href="http://www.networkworld.com/community/node/58218">In open source software engineering, the statistics are worse: only 1.5&ndash;5% are female.</a></p>

<p>One of the organizations which presented at the Google Summer of Code Mentor Summit was the <a href="http://gnome.org/opw/">GNOME Foundation's Outreach Program for Women</a> (OPW). OPW is
similar to GSoC, except that OPW doesn't require its applicants to be
students &mdash; or know how to program when the coding period begins. The pay is competitive with GSoC. And of course,
only women can apply.</p>

<p>In the process of our Google Code-In 2013 application, I recruited several female mentors to work with female GCI
students &mdash; not a requirement, but I think it helps to have supportive people involved with whom one can identify. Unfortunately,
we weren't selected for the Code-In (not too disappointing given <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/gci-announce/P73dzsxKdsM">the several venerable and accomplished organizations that were chosen</a>). But we want to have another go, this
time by applying for the Outreach Program for Women.</p>

<p>Here's where we need your help.</p>

<p>Work for a company that might want to support this goal? Show this to your boss. Have him or her get in touch with
us (sciruby.project at gmail dot com).</p>

<p>If you don't work for such a company, but would still like to help, you can also get in touch at the same email address.
As a general rule of thumb, <a href="https://pledgie.com/campaigns/15783">you can always donate via Pledgie</a>, even if you don't
have access to tons of money.</p>

<p>By the way, <a href="/blog/2013/10/25/mentoring-future-computational-power-women-for-gci-2013/">here's a blog post by one of our mentors, Anna Belak</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mentoring future computational power women for GCI 2013]]></title>
    <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/2013/10/25/mentoring-future-computational-power-women-for-gci-2013/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-25T14:09:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://sciruby.com/blog/2013/10/25/mentoring-future-computational-power-women-for-gci-2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My name is Anna, and I'm an engineer and a scientist. I study Materials Science and Engineering at the University of
Michigan; and I graduated from Virginia Tech with a degree in Physics. My thesis project deals with computationally
predicting the properties of materials used in lithium-ion batteries and airplane turbine blades.</p>

<p><img src="http://sciruby.com/images/anna_belak.jpg" title="Anna Belak coding like a boss" /></p>

<p>I'm writing this blog post for SciRuby, but I'm really writing it for the young women out there. SciRuby is applying to
participate in <a href="https://developers.google.com/open-source/gci/">Google's Code-In 2013</a>, which aims to get high school
students involved in the open source movement, and specifically in coding. It's great preparation for college and
beyond — whatever you might choose to study.</p>

<p>I became involved in science because I love figuring stuff out and working with smart, interesting people, and I want
you to get involved, too. Modern science wouldn't be possible without open source software. Moreover, if you learn how
to code, you'll always have a job. Always.</p>

<p>And the cool part is that you don't have to know how to code in order to participate. Many of the tasks involve research
and documentation in science and mathematics — which is a great way to obtain valuable experience for college
applications.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
