<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Releases | SciRuby]]></title>
  <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/categories/releases/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sciruby.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-10-23T20:55:53+09:00</updated>
  <id>http://sciruby.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[SciRuby]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Pre-alpha Release]]></title>
    <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/2011/11/02/first-pre-alpha-release/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-02T21:39:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://sciruby.com/blog/2011/11/02/first-pre-alpha-release</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=3180369">We made it to the top spot on Hacker News</a> on Halloween (three days ago now). We weren't quite prepared for the level of interest generated by that posting, so we've experienced a few growing pains. (Please please please don't send us to Slashdot.) <!--more--></p>

<p>But growing pains are a good thing! They are, of course, the result of growth -- which we like!</p>

<p>We've had experienced Ruby developers coming out of the woodwork and admitting -- albeit only after looking over their shoulders -- that they, too, have secretly been using Ruby for science, and are thrilled about this project.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/noahhl">Noah</a> from 37signals offered an extremely helpful piece of advice. He pointed out the way <a href="http://github.com/antirez/redis">redis</a> uses its <a href="https://github.com/antirez/redis/issues?state=open">issue tracker</a> to facilitate contributions from people who aren't as familiar with the project status. So now if you want to get involved, instead of checking the Roadmap, you should check the <a href="https://github.com/sciruby/sciruby/issues?sort=created&amp;direction=desc&amp;state=open">SciRuby issue tracker</a>.</p>

<p>We had a couple of people who indicated confusion over what features had already been implemented in SciRuby. The source of the confusion was most likely that we hadn't released a gem in a while, but had still been updating the master branch in the repository.</p>

<p>Our plan had been to wait until we had numeric array and matrix support ready before releasing another gem version. But we capitulated, and have now put out a "pre-alpha," version 0.1.3, available through your friendly neighborhood RubyGems. As of this posting, the v0.1.3 tag corresponds to the code in master.</p>

<h2>Features</h2>

<h3>Plotter GUI</h3>


<p>The most useful feature is probably Plotter, which is a GUI for Rubyvis. You can instantiate it in a couple of different ways. I prefer this one:</p>

<pre><code>sciruby-plotter my_test_plot.rb
</code></pre>


<p>You can modify your source file and the plotter should automatically update the plot. If you want to save your plot, push the 's' key.</p>

<p>Similar to the plotter is a basic Rubyvis code editor. You can instantiate it from irb by calling <code>SciRuby::Editor.new</code>.</p>

<h3>Datasets</h3>


<p>We thought it would be super cool if SciRuby could be used for a lot of those examples people used to write for R. You know, R has all those cool datasets, like <a href="http://stat.ethz.ch/R-manual/R-patched/library/datasets/html/faithful.html">Old Faithful's eruption times</a>.</p>

<pre><code>faithful = SciRuby::dataset(:r, 'faithful')
</code></pre>


<p>You might be wondering, "Why do you have to indicate that it comes from R if it only loads R datasets?" Wonder no more.</p>

<p>I wrote a module for searching online databases for useful datasets as well. It's very buggy. Right now it only works on the <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world-government-data">Guardian World Government Data repository</a>, which is itself somewhat flaky. In other words, this feature might get removed unless some people express an interest in improving it.</p>

<h3>Statistical Analysis DSL</h3>


<p>Claudio Bustos' <a href="http://ruby-statsample.rubyforge.org/statsample/Statsample/Analysis.html">Statsample::Analysis</a> has been migrated into SciRuby. It should eventually ease the transition to SciRuby for those who are familiar with R.</p>

<p>It should work almost exactly the same way as the version from Statsample, but you'll call it with <code>SciRuby::Analysis</code> instead of <code>Statsample::Analysis</code>.</p>

<h2>Installation</h2>

<p>As always, if you want to install SciRuby, you should look at the <a href="/docs#installation">installation instructions</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
